Good afternoon.
We're still ahead but for us the דף daf for today will
be י"ד פ"ח Yud Daled Peh Chet and we pick up the
bottom of פ"ז עמוד ב Peh Zayin Amud Bet and another משנה.
mishna. And we are still dealing with the הפרה hafara between husband
and wife. And let's take a look at this, and this is
a משנה mishna we've quoted before.
יודע אני שיש נדרים. Yodea ani sheyesh nedarim. The man says, you
know, I know that there are things that constitute a הלכתי halachic
נדר. neder. אבל איני יודע שיש מפרים. Aval eini yodea sheyesh mefirim.
I don't know that there's such an idea of הפרה, hafara, that
there's anybody who's empowered to be מפר. meifer. Or maybe he says
I don't know that I'm empowered to be מפר. meifer. I thought,
I don't know, maybe that was some ancient biblical law. I didn't
think it was still applicable or whatever I thought. So, I was
not aware that that was relevant at all to me. So יפה,
yafeh, he can still be מפר meifer because basically the point being
it's not considered יום שמעו, yom shamo, the day that he hears.
So the day that he realizes that he has that power, that's
considered to be the day that he hears, which is interesting because
you could say, well, if maybe you know, it's all or nothing,
which we'll get to in the second part of the משנה, mishna,
but like, you know, if you broke up the physical act of
hearing from the implication and the meaning and the fact that, you
know, what it allows you, maybe neither day is יום שמעו yom
shamo and you're stuck. Okay, we'll talk about that in a minute.
But anyway, here it says not that way. If you don't realize
that you're in the פרשה, parsha, you don't feel that the whole
thing is... you don't even know of a whole world of הפרה,
hafara, or that you don't think that the whole world of הפרה
hafara is relevant to you, then it's like you didn't even hear
it. And therefore the day that he does realize, that's the day
he hears and that's the day he can be מפר. meifer.
I don't know if I should tell this story, but anyway, I
had a friend once who got a ticket for driving on a...
he was moving and he was driving his U-Haul on a parkway.
Is it the parkways that you're not allowed to have commercial vehicles?
Right. So he was driving on a parkway, so he got a
ticket for driving a commercial vehicle. So he... when he appeared, he
went to court.
So he said not guilty. So he's asked why. He says two
reasons. He says number one is I didn't see, you know, I
didn't see the sign. You know, there's no sign, no commercial vehicles.
He says what do you mean the sign right there. He says
well, you know, even if I saw them, I didn't register them
because I assumed that who knew, you know, that a U-Haul was
a commercial vehicle, right? So he said, well, you're required to know.
He says okay, but I didn't know so I didn't even see
the sign, it didn't even register for me. So then he turns
to the judge and says let me ask you a question. How
many handicap stalls are there in the bathroom? In the bathroom right
back here. He says I don't know. He says why not? There
are signs, you'd not know. So if you don't realize it's relevant
for you, you're not even... it doesn't even register. So the judge
says not guilty. Okay. So
anyway, so it was too much of like
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham חאפ, chap, but anyway, nevertheless, point being
if you don't think it's relevant for you, you're not even reading
it, it's not even registering. It's not like oh, I heard but
you know whatever. It's like at some level, it's not even really
registering.
You had a court position, right? He said and of a case
and it's a question whether it allows somebody to be a witness.
And the lawyer said it was about a traffic accident. And so
the lawyer against that witness having that person be a witness said,
do you have a driver's license? The person said no. Ruled out.
Wow. Like you couldn't really appreciate, understand what you were seeing. Right.
So if you don't think it's relevant to you, you're not registering
it. So when you understand it and you hear and you realize
it's relevant, that's the יום שמעו. yom shamo. Now the more interesting
is the split in the end of the משנה. mishna. Let's take
a look. יודע אני שיש מפרים אבל איני יודע שזה נדר. Yodea
ani sheyesh mefirim aval eini yodea shezeh neder. I know that I
can be מפר. meifer. I know that I'm empowered to be מפר.
meifer. I didn't realize that this הלכתית halachically was a נדר. neder.
You know, I thought she missed the key word, I thought you
have to say קונם, konam, I didn't realize if you don't say
קונם konam it could still be a נדר. neder. Or I didn't
think that this was דברים שבינו לבינה. devarim shebeino leveinah. I thought
that this wasn't the types of things. But at least you were
in the פרשה, parsha, you realized you had that power, you realized
that this had the potential of being a נדר. neder. You just
were... didn't think that the specifics made you think that it wasn't
relevant. But fundamentally, you knew that this was your world and so
is that considered to be
יום שמעו yom shamo if you misunderstood the details? So it says
like this, רבי מאיר אומר לא יפר, Rabbi Meir omer lo yafer,
he cannot be מפר. meifer. חכמים אומרים יפר, Chachamim omrim yafer, he
can be מפר. meifer. Now the question is when. So the רן
Ran has two very different explanations of this. I'll give you the
second one first because to me that's just I think the simplest
one, that it follows the point of the first part of the
משנה, mishna, which is let's start with the חכמים. Chachamim. The חכמים
Chachamim that say you can be מפר meifer means when you realize
it. So when tomorrow or three days from now you realize oh,
that actually הלכתית halachically was a נדר, neder, that's considered יום שמעו
yom shamo and you can be מפר meifer just like in the
רישא. reisha. When you put the pieces together, that's יום שמעו. yom
shamo. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you can't be מפר. meifer.
Why? Why can't you be מפר? meifer? Because presumably what he would
say is that you heard it enough on that day itself because
you realized you were in the פרשה, parsha, so that's the יום
שמעו. yom sham'o. Now, can you be מפר meifer and not later?
Because once you heard and you knew you were in the פרשה,
parsha, that's יום שמעו. yom sham'o. Could you be מפר meifer that
day itself, according to רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Why wouldn't you? Probably.
I mean, the question is why would you if you thought it
wasn't relevant, unless you were like, "I don't really think this is
relevant but my wife is begging me to be מפר, meifer, so
I'll go ahead and I'll, you know, I'll make her happy, I'll
be מפר," meifer, or something like that. And you happened to be
מפר, meifer, or you yourself did it just in case. I want
to make it that not you yourself did it just in case
because then it would be that you actually would reflect that you
have real doubt as to whether it was relevant. But let's say
you're doing it because your wife was saying, "please, please just be
מפר, meifer, it'll make me feel better, whatever," and you did it.
Okay, so then presumably according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it would
be fine. Then presumably there's a debate whether this is considered יום
שמעו yom sham'o or not when you know you're in the פרשה
parsha but you don't know that the specific נדר neder is relevant.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that day is יום שמעו, yom sham'o,
you can't do it later. The חכמים Chachamim say no, it's not
יום שמעו yom sham'o until you put all the pieces together. That's
the simplest way of understanding it. The second explanation that the ר"ן
Ran offers is that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir actually says you can't
be מפר meifer tomorrow when you understand, realize it's a נדר, neder,
and you can't be מפר meifer today. Because either way, even if
you wanted to, even if your wife was begging you, I mean
you could do it but it wouldn't count. And the reason is
because today is enough יום שמעו yom sham'o because you realize you
were in the פרשה parsha that you can't make tomorrow יום שמעו,
yom sham'o, but today is not enough יום שמעו yom sham'o that
you could be מפר meifer because you don't have all the pieces
together. So you're a little bit caught in between. Okay, that's what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
What?
We're saying that, where do we know that fundamentally
שמעו sham'o means that you realize that it's relevant to you? Yeah,
I mean, that's a good question. You could ask that at the
רישא reisha of the משנה, mishna, right? You physically heard it. Okay,
somehow חז"ל Chazal understand, you know, the difference between hearing and listening.
You know, hearing means a meaningful type of hearing. But you're right,
it's not giving us any מדרש הלכה midrash halacha to tell us
why we know that. Okay, so that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So
the ר"ן Ran says according to that read, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says it's like in the beginning of the משנה mishna where if
you didn't realize you were in the פרשה, parsha, it was nothing.
But when you realize you're in the פרשה, parsha, that's יום שמעו.
yom sham'o. Enough that you can't do it tomorrow, but not enough
that you can do it today because it's not a full שמיעה.
shmi'ah. Okay, so you split it up into two half-שמיעות shmi'ahs and
neither one is enough. And the חכמים Chachamim would say according to
this read, that no, he can be מפר meifer according to this
read, חכמים Chachamim actually would be saying that he can be מפר
meifer on the day that he hears. Again, if he's doing it
because his wife is pressuring him even though he doesn't think it's
relevant, etc. So according to that read, the חכמים Chachamim actually are
saying that it is יום שמעו yom sham'o and it's enough יום
שמעו yom sham'o that he actually be מפר meifer on that day.
So those two very different reads, whether basically רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is saying you can't be מפר meifer at all and the חכמים
Chachamim are saying you could be מפר meifer on the day you
hear, or that no, the whole question is throughout the day that
you put the pieces together, there רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that
doesn't count, the חכמים Chachamim say it does.
Yes, I understand the second case a little bit. If this was
the type of situation where he'd be thinking, "Okay, well, I know,
I know like, you know, I can be מפר meifer a נדר,
neder, I just didn't think this was a נדר," neder, as opposed
to if he would have said, "Oh, I didn't even know you
can be מפר meifer נדרים, nedarim, I only knew you could be
מפר meifer a שבועה," shvua, then they'd both be in agreement, right?
One more time, you say said what?
In other words, he knew that there's such an idea of הפרה
hafarah and there's such an idea for a נדר, neder, but he
just didn't know this was a נדר, neder, right? Right. But if
he only thought there was הפרה hafarah for שבועות shvuot and not
נדרים, nedarim, and his wife makes a נדר... neder...
Yeah, then presumably,
presumably that would be the case. Okay, so let's see the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara is going to analyze this or like
ask the question on these last opinions, but it's as we said,
it's a little bit unclear what those last opinions are exactly holding.
רמינהו, Rami'ihu, says the גמרא, Gemara, I'll ask you on this. בלא
ראות. blow ra'ot. This is somebody who basically accidentally kills somebody and
he goes into גלות, golus, and it says that he killed this
person בלא ראות, blow ra'ot, without seeing him. He was there chopping
wood in the forest and he didn't see the guy and the
blade flew off of the handle and he accidentally killed him. So
בלא ראות, פרט לסומא, B'lo re'ot prat lasuma, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says this actually excludes a
סומא. suma. Why? Because a סומא suma also, I mean a סומא
suma doesn't see, but בלא ראות blow ra'ot, means you didn't see
and you otherwise you should have seen, you had the ability to
see, you could have seen, but you didn't. So if somebody's actually
blind, they couldn't have even seen if they had wanted, then they
would not be liable in this case. What's he doing chopping wood?
Well, I don't know, some blind people have that, you know, are
very capable in terms of that. So רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir
omer, לרבות את הסומא. l'rabot et hasuma. No, בלא ראות blow ra'ot
includes a סומא. suma. Now how does, how does בלא ראות blow
ra'ot include the סומא? suma? Maybe it just means בלא ראות, blow
ra'ot he didn't see, anybody who didn't see including a סומא. suma.
Or maybe, but the point more being and this is why the
גמרא Gemara thinks that this is relevant to our discussion, that רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it seems to say that the debate here is
a blind person has an awareness without seeing, so it's like a
partial but not a full awareness, and therefore the גמרא's Gemara comparing
it in a way to the this partial seeing of a blind
person, I'm using seeing metaphorically, you know, to the partial hearing of
this person on the day when he hears but he doesn't really
think that it's relevant to him. And the way the הר"ן HaRan
explains it, I'm going to go with the second explanation I gave
you for the debate because that just fits more smoothly in this,
is that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says, right, the second way I
explained it, you can't annul today, you can't annul tomorrow. Each one
is only half of a hearing. So it's enough of a hearing
that tomorrow you can't say that's the day I heard because you
already started the hearing yesterday. And on the day that you heard
you can't say that's the day I heard because you didn't hear
yet completely. So you have to break it up into two halves.
So that basically means that, you know, a partial doesn't count. And
the חכמים Hachamim say no, on the day you heard, even though
you don't or aren't aware of the specifics, that's enough of a
hearing that you can. And so that's sort of saying that a
partial you can get. Again, that's assuming that the חכמים Hachamim are
saying in the second case of the משנה, Mishnah, the חכמים Hachamim
say you can do it the day you hear, because partial is
enough. And רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says you can't do it on
the day you hear or on the next day because each one
is a partial and a partial is not enough. So the הר"ן
HaRan says well that's, so given that explanation of the debate, that's
the exact contradiction of what they said about the blind person. There
רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, who presumably is the חכמים Hachamim against רבי
מאיר, Rebbi Meir, says that partial isn't enough. If the guy is
blind and he has partial awareness,
he's not considered to have sufficient awareness and he's exempt, whereas רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir says partial awareness is like he's aware, it's just,
it counts, it's the same, it's enough of that awareness that the
תורה Torah is assuming that a blind person has and therefore he's
going to be in the פרשה, Parsha, he's going to be liable.
So how are you switching sides? In one case, you know, that's
very funny, I mean, who the heck says that in these radically
different areas of הלכה Halacha we would define these things in the
same way? Besides the fact that there's a פסוק Pasuk here which
seems to be pushing us in, you know, in a particular area
specifically for this. But anyway, this is how the הר"ן HaRan says
the debate is. In our משנה Mishnah רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
partial, two partials, each partial is nothing, and the חכמים Hachamim say
no, the first partial which is the real initial awareness, that suffices.
And by the blind person, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is
saying that the partial counts and the חכמים Hachamim are saying the
partial does not count. So let's take a look at how we
do this. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says רבא, Rava, top of
פ"א עמוד א׳, Pey Aleph Amud Aleph, הכא מעניינא דקרא והכא מעניינא
דקרא. Hacha me'inyana de'kra v'hacha me'inyana de'kra. In each case, you go
based on the implications of the verse. Now, when it has that
double language, it sounds like there's one verse that dictates to us
for גלות Galut and there's another verse that dictates to us for
נדרים, Nedarim, but that actually is not true. We're not going to
quote any verse by נדרים, Nedarim, as Michael pointed out or whatever,
we're just saying this statement in the משנה Mishnah with no biblical
basis, okay, with no showing how it comes from the verse. So
really it's basically so saying that the issue about the גלות Galut
and the blind person is specifically responding to the language of the
פסוק Pasuk and therefore is not really relevant to this more general
debate that we have in our משנה. Mishnah. So let's take a
look. רבי יהודה סבר גבי רוצח כתיב. Rebbi Yehuda savar gabi rotzeach
ketiv. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says look, by the murderer it says,
ואשר יבוא את רעהו ביער, V'asher yavo et re'ehu baya'ar, and the
person who comes upon his friend in the forest.
כל דבר מעיילי ליער, Kol d'bar me'ilei laya'ar,
anybody who would be a person who enters into the forest. Okay,
so that's a very inclusive phrase, anybody who comes upon his friend
in the forest. סומא נמי בר מעיילי ליער הוא, Suma nami bar
me'ilei laya'ar hu, and that would include a blind person, right? Anybody
who enters into a forest. So fundamentally the פרשה Parsha by the
גלות Galut starts with assuming a blind person is included. ואי אמרת
בלא ראות לרבות את הסומא. V'ei amrat b'lo re'ot l'rabot et hasuma.
Now, what do I do when I get later in the פרשה
Parsha to the word בלא ראות, blow ra'ot, without seeing? If without
seeing means that even somebody who can't see, like a blind person,
I wouldn't have needed the פסוק Pasuk to include that. מיער נפקא
ליה, M'yaar nafka lei, I've already learned that from the word יער,
Ya'ar, from forest. אלא שמע מינה, Ela shma mina, if it's saying
without seeing, I can infer בלא ראות B'lo re'ot, פרט לסומא, prat
l'suma, that the only thing the פסוק Pasuk is left to do
now since I started by including the blind person would be to
exclude the blind person. Okay,
something like that. רבי מאיר סבר, Rebbi Meir savar, and now we're
going to do the reverse for רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. כתיב בבלי
דעת. Ketiv b'bli da'at. No, it starts by saying that he would
kill somebody without awareness, okay. כל דבר מדע, Kol d'bar meda, anybody
that is a person who can be aware, meaning and he's understanding
it to be fully aware. וסומא לאו בר מדע הוא, V'suma lav
bar meda hu, and a blind person cannot be fully aware. So
I start by reading the פרשה Parsha assuming a blind person is
excluded. ואי אמרת בלא ראות פרט לסומא. V'ei amrat b'lo re'ot prat
lasuma. Now, if בלא ראות b'lo re'ot comes to exclude a blind
person, מבבלי דעת נפקא ליה, M'b'bli da'at nafka lei, I've already excluded
a blind person because I started by assuming that you needed to
be somebody who was fully aware. So if I started by assuming
fully aware and now I get בלא ראות b'lo re'ot coming, the
only thing left for it to do is to include a blind
person. שמע מינה shema mina ובלוא ראות u'velo ra'os לרבות lerabos את
הסומא es hasuma is coming to include a blind person. So Michael
is right, this is a nice spell-out on both sides of the
coin here, the equation here of the principle of אין מיעוט אחר
מיעוט אלא לרבות ein miyut achar miyut ela lerabos and אין ריבוי
אחר ריבוי אלא למעט. ein ribui achar ribui ela lema'et. Right? So
if I already know something's an exclusion and I exclude it again,
it can't be coming to exclude, it's already been excluded, it must
be coming to include. Or if I've already known something is included
and then I have a verse to include it again, I don't
need it for that, so it must be coming to exclude. Now,
so this basically just says, look, give me a break. We're just
דורש doreshing פסוקים pesukim here, by גלות galus it's not relevant. But
what the ר"ן Ran does is he actually says, not only is
it that it's not relevant, but actually maybe specifically there're different approaches
to partial awareness and partial knowledge informs how they read the פסוק
pasuk by גלות. galus. Why? If what we were saying was correct,
that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says 'the day you hear' is partial
hearing and partial doesn't count, right? So רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir of
the basic position that partial doesn't count. So he starts reading the
פרשה parsha by גלות, galus, פרשה פרשה, parsha parsha, he starts by
reading the whole section by גלות galus to exclude a blind person,
because his normal approach is partial isn't enough. So my initial look
at who is the פרשה parsha talking about by גלות galus by
being aware, it's not a blind person because my initial approach is
partial doesn't suffice. Then I've got an extra פסוק, pasuk, that must
be coming to pull him in. So because he started by saying
partial isn't enough, he wound up pulling him in by גלות. galus.
And רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is the opposite. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says 'the day you hear,' it's partial, but it's enough.
And again, if you weren't aware at all that it was relevant
for you, it's not like you heard at all. But if you
were aware that you were, had the ability, but you didn't know
that this specifically fell into that category, that's partial, partial is enough.
So רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda starts with the idea, partial hearing, partial
awareness is meaningful. So he starts by assuming that a blind person
is in the category of גלות galus because he starts by assuming
partial is enough. Then you've got an extra פסוק, pasuk, that extra
פסוק pasuk has to state, can only be excluding. So actually, in
a way, what the גמרא's Gemara saying, you're right, the positions are
reversed. But it's because of position A, the פסוק pasuk winds up
pushing you into the opposite conclusion as where you would have started.
And that's how תוספות... Tosafos... Well right, that's essentially the way the
ר"ן Ran is reading the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, let's
now look at the next
משנה. Mishna. המדיר הנאה מחתנו, hamadir hana'ah mechasno, somebody vows that his
son-in-law cannot get any הנאה hana'ah from him. Again the word מ
mi is a little funny. We always wind up getting the prepositions
in the
reverse, right? So but here, so if you look at the side,
תוספות Tosafos in another place has a גרסא girsa which is המדיר
חתנו הנאה ממנו, hamadir chasno hana'ah mimenu, which is more grammatically accurate
although I'm not sure that it's actually more original. But anyway, somebody
takes a vow that his son-in-law can't get any benefit from him.
Okay, all my property is forbidden to my son-in-law.
Okay. What about father-in-law?
How do you say father-in-law?
חמי. chami. Okay.
I know, in the תורה, Torah, חותן chosen can also mean father-in-law.
Okay. והוא רוצה לתת לבתו מעות, v'hu rotze lates l'bito ma'os, but
I wanted to give some money to my daughter. But if I
give money to my daughter, there's a problem because the principle is
כל שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה, kol shekansah isha kanah ba'alah, that if
my daughter takes possession of property her husband winds up owning it.
Now, the point might be, it might not be that he directly
owns it and puts it straight in his bank account. As you
might remember, the principle is that if a woman brings property into
the marriage, the husband is אוכל פירות. ochel peiros. She retains title,
but he gets any of the benefit from the property. So if
I give my daughter a thousand dollars, what we might say is,
you have to go ahead and use that, buy an investment property,
and you'll maintain title, but your husband will get the income. Or,
I don't know, put it in some type of a put it
in a bank account and get some interest, like what, what are
they giving now? .01 percent? Anyway, and your husband gets the interest.
But even if she retains title, if the husband is getting the
פירות, peiros, so he's getting benefit from my property. Okay, so therefore,
what are we going to do? So אמר לה, amar lah, so
he says to her, הרי המעות האלו נתונים לך במתנה ובלבד שלא
יהא לבעלך רשות בהן. harei hama'os ha'elu nesunim lach b'matana u'vilvad shelo
yehei l'va'alech reshus bahen. These are given to you as a gift,
but your husband is to not have any control over it. So
apparently if he gives it explicitly to his
daughter with the explicit condition that the husband has no rights over
it, then the husband will have no rights. However...
What? Well no, the כתובה kesubah is about property she brings into...
But besides that, the כתובה kesubah doesn't mention
the פירות נכסי מלוג, peiros nichsei milog, that's just an ongoing, it
doesn't list the things she has title, it's just a natural consequence,
anything she has title, he's אוכל פירות. ochel peiros. But this actually
does get to that question: is specifically stipulating against it enough? So
the משנה Mishna then ends the phrase, אלא מה שאת נושאת ונותנת
לפיך. ela mah she'at noses v'nosenses l'fich. All you get, all you
have... Is what you put in your mouth. Now what does that
mean? So the way the רן Ran *Ran* explains it is, saying
I'm not giving your husband any rights doesn't do the job because
maybe like we'll see basically the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to say
that this משנה Mishna *Mishnah*'s going according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir,
*Rabbi Meir* that קנת אשה *kanat isha* יד אשה כיד בעלה yad
isha ke-yad baalah, *yad isha kyad baalah* and that maybe it can't
even be stipulated against. You see there's an interesting conceptual question here,
which is, when we say קנת אשה קנה בעלה *kanat isha kana
baalah*, do we say fundamentally she has her own יד yad, *yad*,
she's her own person, and she basically fundamentally it's, you know, deposits
the money in her own account. It's just that we've got an
automatic...
it's a joint account.
We've got... no, not a joint account, it's like... it's like call
forwarding, okay? It's like email forwarding, okay? If you send... I mean,
I assume you can set up your bank account like this. Email
forwarding: the email actually first goes into inbox one, but then it
automatically goes... gets sent to inbox two. So she basically's got her
own bank account, got her own יד yad, *yad*. She takes possession
of thing. It's set up that as soon as it goes into
her bank account it gets transferred to her husband's. Okay, that's one
idea. The other idea is that קנת אשה קנה בעלה *kanat isha
kana baalah*. To say that more radically, you would say יד אשה
כיד בעלה yad isha ke-yad baalah *yad isha kyad baalah*. She doesn't
even have her own joint account bank account. As soon as she
takes something, takes it, it gets deposited into her husband's bank account.
She's basically an extension of her husband. So, if you say the
first model, you might be able to interrupt the... the call forwarding,
the automatic transfer. You might be able to say, I'm going to
deposit it in your account and I'm going to stipulate that it
can't get forwarded. Okay, then maybe that would suffice and then the
husband doesn't get anything. Okay, but if it directly goes over to
the husband,
then you... how can you interrupt that? She's auto... she's just an
extension of the husband. She has none of her own, you know,
sort of halachic legal standing. So then the רן Ran *Ran* says
that's why you actually have to say כל מה שאת נושאת ונותנת
בפיך be-picha, *kol mah sheat noset venotenet bepicha*. Basically the way רן
Ran *Ran* explains what that condition is is, I'm not even really
giving it to you. What I'm really saying is, here's this money,
it's totally on loan, I haven't really given you anything yet. Go
ahead and buy yourself some food and as you're putting and that
food is mine too. But as you're putting that food in your
mouth, then I'm going to let you benefit from it. Not your
husband, only you can benefit from it. So I don't even know
even at that minute, is she eating her own food or is
she eating her father-in-law's food? Okay, maybe she... her father... maybe even
there she's eating her father's food. But whatever she's doing, it's doing
it in a way that only you take possession of it when
you're directly benefiting from it and therefore it doesn't have a chance
to transfer to your... you know, to your husband. That's the way
he understands it. Now, the question is, is פיך *picha* literally is
an interesting question, that
go to
the
store and buy a dress. So that's a question that the רן
Ran *Ran* discusses. Maybe if it's a non-consumable,
right, maybe it is a problem because then she's wearing the dress,
so now she owns a dress and now the husband has some
rights to that dress. Maybe it's only in case of a consumable
or maybe not. Maybe even if it's a dress, you know, basically
it's like it's her father's dress, her father's just letting her wear
the father's dress and therefore ultimately you never get to the problem
of it becoming the husband's. So that might be based on that
question of does she ever take possession of it at any stage.
Okay, but yes, so that's a question whether פיך *picha* if it
might if it's only פיך *picha* might mean because she is going
to take possession but only as the moment she's consuming it, as
opposed to if you say that no, I'm always going to own
it, I the father, then she can only then maybe she can
wear the dress because it's my dress that she's wearing. Anyways, that's
how the רן Ran *Ran* explained it and the reason is normally
we would think and there's actually a position and we'll discuss in
a minute how we פוסקין *paskin* that it's just enough to say
to give something to a woman and say שאין לבעלך רשות reshut.
בהן *she-ein lebaalcha reshut bahen* and that works and then she possesses
it and the... and the... and the husband gets no rights, no
control, no benefit out of it. Our משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* assumes that
you need more and you need this additional phrase of נושאת ונותנת
לתוך פיך *noset venotenet letoch picha*. One other point before we look
at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is why does the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* say מעות *maot*? So the
רן Ran *Ran* says because had he wanted to give his daughter
directly food, he wouldn't have had to make any stipulation. Why? Not
because of the נושאת ונותנת לתוך פיך *noset venotenet letoch picha*. Let's
say he just directly gave her food and she totally took possession
of it. So why wouldn't the husband have some rights to it?
Because the husband is obligated to feed his wife. So therefore when
he's feeding his wife, if I go ahead and I put a
steak on the table to my wife, I give it to my
wife and says, ah, but you know what, even now that I'm
feeding you, I'm still entitled to the benefit of that steak. The
very fact that my... I have an obligation to pay for the
food means that what I am giving her in for her food
bill, for her food, is something that I don't have rights to.
That's what I have to give over to her. Right, that I
have to take... is that it's totally not mine, it has to
totally be me giving to her. So therefore he says if the
father wants to give her food, her food is something that if
it's directly food, not money, is something that the husband... that's satisfying
the husband's obligation and therefore something the husband has no rights over.
But is he benefiting from the fact that he doesn't have to
pay now?
Yeah, but that's מבריח ארי *mavriach ari*. That's a good question. But
you might remember that's מבריח ארי *mavriach ari*, that indirectly you're not
giving me anything, you're doing something that
Okay. Anyway, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara, אמר
רב, Amar Rav, לא שנו אלא דאמר לה מה שאת נושאת ונותנת
בפיך. lo shanu ela de-amar lah ma she-at noset ve-notenet be-picha. Only
if he says בפיך, thank you. If he says what you put
into your mouth. אבל אמר מה שתרצי עשי, aval amar ma she-tirtsi
asi, if he says 'do what you want with them' and he
doesn't really have that other explicit stipulation of putting in your mouth,
in that case, קנה בהן בעל, kana bahen baal, the father, the
husband takes possession of it, meaning that you cannot not have that
last phrase. Again, I'll read this גמרא Gemara, first like the ר"ן
Ran and then, which is the simplest way, which basically means if
you just said, if he says 'do what you want', that's sort
of like saying על מנת שאין לבעלך רשות בהן. al menat she-ein
le-baalcha reshut bahen. So meaning if you have just the idea 'your
husband doesn't have any rights, do what you want', etc. but you
don't have that last phrase, then you got a problem, then the
husband takes possession. You can't stipulate against that. The only way you
can stop the husband from taking possession is the way described in
the משנה Mishna where basically she doesn't take possession until the moment
she's consuming it. ושמואל אמר, u-Shmuel amar, now שמואל Shmuel says, אפילו
אמר מה שתרצי עשי, afilu amar ma she-tirtsi asi, even if he
says 'do what you want', which again we're going to read this
assuming that that's the same of 'on this condition your husband has
no rights', okay? He basically says 'it's totally yours, not your husband's,
do what you want', etc. but he does not say that you
don't possess until you eat it. Nevertheless, if you just say 'do
what you want and your husband doesn't have rights', לא קנה בהן
בעל, lo kana bahen baal, the husband does not take possession. Okay,
and this the גמרא Gemara seems is basically the debate of whether
we say how fully we say יד אשה כיד בעלה, yad isha
ke-yad baalah, like I was saying before. So the ר"ן Ran says,
claims, that שמואל Shmuel is not arguing on the משנה. Mishna The
משנה Mishna. says you need to say both things. The way the
ר"ן Ran reads this גמרא, Gemara, we'll give a different reason in
a read in a minute, but the way the ר"ן Ran reads
this גמרא, Gemara שמואל Shmuel is actually saying: 'As far as the
משנה Mishna. is concerned, I concede the point. The משנה Mishna. thinks
that the husband's rights over his wife's property are complete, and the
only way you keep the husband away is by this crazy stipulation
of "as you're putting it in your mouth". But as a matter
of הלכה, halacha, I think we don't rule like the משנה. mishna
As a matter of הלכה, halacha, as long as you say "if
he doesn't have rights", that's enough to keep the husband out of
the picture.' And רב Rav says: 'No, as a matter of הלכה
halacha I rule like the משנה. Mishnah. I think that the husband's
rights are much more complete and there's really almost no way to
keep the husband out of the picture except for the way stipulated
in the משנה.' So let's take a look. So this is really
just going to get to this point about how complete are the
husband's rights over what his wife possesses. מתקיף לה רבי זירא. Matkif
lah Rabbi Zeira. So רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira challenged the following way.
כמאן אזלא השמעתא דרב. ke-man azla ha-shmaita de-Rav.
רב's Rav approach that says that you need to say 'as you're
putting it in your mouth', it's not sufficient to say 'keep it
to yourself and your husband has no rights'. Who's that going like?
כרבי מאיר, ke-Rabbi Meir, like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דאמר יד אשה
כיד בעלה. de-amar yad isha ke-yad baalah. The wife's hand is like
her husband's hand. Like I said, that is a more of a,
that's a stronger statement. יד אשה כיד בעלה yad isha kyad ba'alah,
is a stronger statement than
מה שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה. ma she-kantah isha kanah baalah. Okay. This
says she's got her own hand. Now I get to draw my
nice little... Okay. She's got her own hand, there you go, that's
her hand. Okay. It goes here and then it gets to her
husband. Okay. That's מה שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה. ma she-kantah isha kanah
baalah. She gets it and then it goes to her husband. Okay.
It's automatic forwarding. It goes into her bank account, okay?
Here's שרה's Sarah bank account, okay? And here's אברהם's. Avraham Okay. So
she has a bank account, she's just got it set up for
automatic call forwarding. So it gets deposited into her bank account and
then it goes to his. Okay. That's מה שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה.
ma she-kantah isha kanah baalah. If that's true, maybe you could deposit
into her bank account and stipulate and say 'this won't get forwarded
to your husband'. Okay, then you don't need any bigger stipulation. But
יד אשה כיד בעלה, basically means like sort of like אשתו כגופו,
ishto ke-gufo, okay? Basically
means here's her hand, but really it's just like his hand. Okay.
So anything that's going into her hand is just going straight into
his bank account. Okay. So how do you stop that? It's she's
seen as his hand. So maybe the only way you don't stop
it, and all you can say is it's only yours the moment
you're consuming it. And then if she's consuming it, there's nothing to
go to him at that moment. Okay. So let's take a look.
So כמאן אזלא השמעתא דרב, ke-man azla ha-shmaita de-Rav, כרבי מאיר, ke-Rabbi
Meir, דאמר יד אשה כיד בעלה. de-amar yad isha ke-yad baalah. ורמינהו,
u-reminhu, I'll ask you on this.
כיצד משתתפין במבוי. keitsad mishtatfin be-mavoi. This is a סתם משנה stam
Mishna which we're going to assume is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir. because
we assume סתם משנה stam Mishna is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir So
how do you make a שיתוף מבואות? shituf mevo'ot? Okay, everybody who
wishes we could get back to עירובין Eruvin and all those fun
pictures. Anyway, the basic point is like this. You have a lot
of courtyards. Each of these courtyards has houses that open up into
a shared courtyard. These are חצר. chatzer. Okay, and all of these
courtyards open up into a shared alleyway, okay, and the alleyway is
the מבוי. mavoi. Okay, and this, here's what we make it a
מבוי סתום, mavoi satum, so it's got, so it's got, it's dead-ended,
so you can make it into a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay,
and you're going to go ahead and put up a little, a
little לחי lechi or a קורה, kora, you're going to make a
צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, whatever, you got a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
here. This area here is shared with the alley with all of
the חצר. chatzer. Now, the point is, is that the same way
if in the individual חצרות, chatzerot, the courtyard, the courtyard is shared
with all the houses, so in order to make it considered to
be a, it is a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid technically in that
it's surrounded by walls, but it's not a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
experientially because a lot of different people have rights to it, people
of separate households have rights to it. So in order to make
it feel like a singular household-like domain, everybody joins together in like
a loaf of bread and it makes it like they're all are
equal, like it's a unified corporation, single entity that has rights, not
a lot of separate homes that have rights into the, you know,
to the courtyard. So the same is true about the alleyway. All
of the חצרות chatzerot have to all contribute to some joint food,
okay, and therefore it's like they're all one corporate entity sharing the
חצר, chatzer, not distinct units. All right. So how do you take
this thing of food, which we're going to say like is a
barrel of wine, and make it owned by all of the חצרות?
chatzerot? So you could go around and collect a little wine from
everybody, but here's a simpler way.
Okay. כיצד משתתפין במבוי? Keitzad mishtatfin bamavoi? How do you make a
שיתוף, shituf, a partnership within the מבוי? mavoi?
מניח את החבית, Meniach et hachavit, you take your barrel of wine,
ואומר, ve'omer, and you say, הרי זה לכל בני המבוי, harei zeh
lechol bnei hamavoi, I am transferring ownership of this to every member
of the מבוי mavoi and therefore they all are equal owners. You
don't have to go collect and knocking door-to-door. You, like the Rabbi,
for example, we have an עירוב eruv in Riverdale. Nobody ever went
to you and asked for a donation to, for the food for
the שיתוף מבואות shituf mevo'ot or the עירוב חצירות. eruv chatzerot. What
the Rabbi does is he takes a box of matzahs, because matzahs
don't get stale too, too long, and he goes ahead and he
gives it to someone and he says, here, take possession of this
box of matzahs for everybody who lives in the community. Okay, I
don't know, maybe. Anyway. All right. So, so you go and you
take, take possession of this barrel of wine for everybody who's in
the מבוי. mavoi. מניח את החבית ואומר הרי זה לכל בני המבוי,
Meniach et hachavit ve'omer harei zeh lechol bnei hamavoi, ומזכה להן על
ידי עבדו ושפחתו העברים. umezakeh lahen al yedei avdo veshifchato ha'ivrim. Now,
you need a third party. You can't just take it from one
hand to the next. In order to do an act of taking
possession, it has to leave your domain, go into somebody else's possession,
and that third party or second party or whatever, can take, can
take possession of it for everyone else. So who is that, who
is that person that's not you? So, I mean, so obviously it
could be a total stranger, but we have to talk about people
that might be seen as an extension of you that are not.
So you can give it to your female or male Hebrew slaves,
which even though, you know, you have rights to them or whatever,
they're not just seen as an extension of you. ועל ידי בנו
ובתו הגדולים, ve'al yedei bno uvito hagedolim, or your adult children, son
or daughter. ועל ידי, ve'al yedei, yes. So the question is whether
גדולים gedolim means literally גדולים gedolim or not, but anyway, those that
are seen to be their own, you know, to be their own
people, halachically have their own sense of ownership and so on. ועל
ידי אשתו, ve'al yedei ishto, or the wife. So here you have
that Rabbi Meir, because we're assuming סתם משנה stam mishna is Rabbi
Meir, assumes that if a husband gives something to his wife,
he's giving it into a different, you know, into a different type
of an entity
and not to himself.
So if you said a woman, the wife has her own hand,
right? So then that's a, she's a distinct יד, a distinct entity
from his, he can give it to her. And then he's saying
before it automatically transfers to me, when you take possession, it gets
owned by everybody. Okay, but if she's just his own hand, it's
like putting it from his right hand to his left hand. So
if Rabbi Meir says that basically יד אשה כיד בעלה, how can
he transfer possession to her in this משנה about the שיתוף מבואות?
shituf mevo'ot? So that's the question. ואי אמרת קנייה שון בעלה, ve'i
amart kneyah shon ba'alah, and if you say that the husband takes
possession even when he says על מנת שאין לבעלך רשות בהן, al
menat she'ein leba'alech reshut bahen, right? So that means that it's fundamentally
all one יד, there's no way to interrupt that connection. So if
that's true, עירוב לא נפיק מרשותיה דבעל. eruv lo nafik mershuteih deba'al.
The עירוב eruv isn't going out of his רשות. So how does
he make it work? How does he stop it? Okay, how does
he, I mean, or how does he, you know, how does he
not stop it? How, you know, how does he make his wife
have her own hand in this context? So אמר רבא, amar Rava,
so Rava says, אף על גב דאמר רבי מאיר יד אשה כיד
בעלה, af al gav de'amar Rabbi Meir yad isha kyad ba'alah, although
Rabbi Meir says the husband's hand is like the wife's hand, the
wife's hand is like the husband's hand, excuse me,
מודה רבי מאיר לעניין שיתוף, modeh Rabbi Meir le'inyan shituf, he agrees
when it comes to
שיתוף, shituf, דכיון דלזכות לאחרים הוא, dekeivan d'lezakot l'acherim hu, because since
it's coming to, to take possession from her husband for other people,
מיד בעלה זכיה, miyad ba'alah zachyah, it works. Now, that sounds a
lot more, you know, descriptive than explanatory. Thank you, we knew that
was what was happening, the husband was giving it to take possession
for others. But still, why does it work? So the question is...
Which of the parts of this phrase of the description do you
think are critical? The ר"ן Ran. and תוספות Tosfos here all emphasize
the מיד בעלה. miyad ba'alah. The husband is explicitly giving it to
her and he's taking it, he's saying "I'm giving it to you,
so I'm taking it out of my control and I want you
in this context to represent something other than me." The whole point
is I'm trying to take it away from me. So basically what
that's saying is that even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say that
even though she's his hand, in theory he's in a position to
basically push her away and to say "I'm breaking that thing." I
can't give something—that's the
way—I don't want my right hand to be part of my body.
Well right, I mean you're right because for example he could not
do it for his non-Hebrew slave, right, for his non-Hebrew slave that's
considered to be his hand, it's like his property and if you
put some—or if I put something on my—in my yard, can I
say "I'm putting it in my yard but I want my yard
to be an independent entity?" You can't. I can't put something on
my Hebrew slave and my non-Hebrew slave and say "I want him
to be an independent entity" because they're fundamentally, right, I mean I
think the way we would sort of say it is that the
status of a slave is property. The woman is not property, right?
She is a—her own subject and person and legal entity in הלכה,
Halacha, right? I mean she can have court cases with other people
while she's married etc. She doesn't stop being a legal entity. So
we see this idea that she's יד בעלה, yad ba'alah, it's a
very good question, but the point I think is, we see this
idea of יד בעלה yad ba'alah as more as a—as something that's
like imposed upon, it's not a natural consequence of marriage. We don't
see her as a property like we sort of see the slave.
Okay, but what we see is we've instituted a structure that will
define her as יד בעלה, yad ba'alah, but that's a type of
a structure that can be removed. Okay, and it doesn't go against
the concept of what it means to be a wife. Okay, so
that's a, you know, so but it is a very good point.
So because this is something that is not necessarily a natural consequence
of what it means to be a wife, okay, it's possible to
have an idea of a wife without יד בעלה, yad ba'alah, but
basically what the—the way that the ר"ן Ran, and תוספות Tosfos are
reading it is the husband is the only one in position to
break that relationship. Okay, so, you know, the husband can basically say
"I am actually going to remove my sort of control here and
let her be her own entity," but you can't do that. If
I haven't agreed to that and you put it in her hand,
you're putting it in my hand. Only if I can say it's
no longer my hand. That's the way the ר"ן and תוספות Tosfos
reads it. So since it's מיד בעלה, miyad ba'alah, the husband is
the one doing it, right, she can go—that works. Now the other
way you could have read the גמרא Gemara is that the emphasis
is not that the husband is doing it, but the emphasis is
לזכות לאחרים, l'zakos l'acherim,
where is it ending up? And that basically would say, if I
am putting it into her hand and I want her to own
it, then רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir would say anything that's going into
her bank account basically goes straight into her husband's. Okay? It leapfrogs
over her own bank account as it were, there's nowhere it can
stay—it can stop in her own bank account. But if I want
her to take possession for the sake of other people, right, then
we don't see that as her husband's hand. Then we sort of
see that as other people's hand. So if she's doing it for
herself, when she's taking possession for things for herself, then she's seen
to be only an extension of her husband. When she's taking possession
for the sake of other people, then she's seen to be more
of an independent entity. So that would emphasize the לזכות לאחרים. l'zakos
l'acherim. But ר"ן and תוספות Tosfos both emphasize the fact that it's
מיד בעלה, miyad ba'alah, the husband can sever that relationship. Another person
cannot. Okay now let's see the—yes?
I was just confused about one point. Are we saying if she's
taking possession, is it only from her husband, or if somebody else
give her and say this is for other people?
So that's the debate—that is the two positions I'm saying. According to
ר"ן and תוספות, Tosfos, a third party could not say "this is
for other people." It is only the husband that can sever that
relationship. According to another way of reading the גמרא, Gemara because the
גמרא Gemara says there's two things going on here: the husband is
the one doing it and it's for other people. So which of
those two criteria is the critical one? ר"ן and תוספות Tosfos say
the critical point here is that the husband is the one who
is doing it. Okay, so that's what he said.
Now the גמרא Gemara clarifies this one step further. Okay. איתיביה רבינא
לרב אשי. Aesivay Ravina l'Rav Ashi. So רבינא Ravina asked רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, not so much as explaining רב Rav's position, but just
as a contradiction of two Tannaic teachings. Okay, because here we have
another—we have a ברייתא. Baraisa. אלו שזכין להן. elu she-zachin lahen. These
are the following people that you can take—be—transfer
the barrel of wine for the sake of the מבוי. mavoi. Who—these
are the people who can do that process? על ידי בנו ובתו
הגדולים, al yedei beno uvito hagedolim, adult children, sons and daughters, ועבדו
ושפחתו העברים, ve'avdo veshifchaso ha'ivrim, your Hebrew slaves, ואלו שאין זכין להן,
ve-elu she-ein zachin lahen, and the following are cannot be part of
this ability to take possession of it: על ידי בנו ובתו הקטנים,
al yedei beno uvito haktanim, minor children. עבדו ושפחתו הכנענים v’avdo v’shifchato
hak’naanim
who are
Canaanite non-Hebrew slaves, ואשתו v’ishto and the wife. So now we got
a problem. We got one ברייתא, Baraita, we got one teaching that
says that the wife can do it, and another Tannaic source saying
that the wife cannot do it. So how do we explain this?
If even רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir. says the wife can do it,
who is the one saying the wife cannot do it here? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רב אשי מתניתין בשיש לה חצר
באותו מבוי עסקינן דמיגו דזכיה לנפשה זכיה לאחרני. Ela amar Rav Ashi
matnitin besheyesh lah chatzer be’oto mavoi askinan demigo dezachyah l’nafshah zachyah l’achrinei.
Even this question of when the husband is giving it to her,
can she represent her own entity? Says רב אשי Rav Ashi is
not true in all cases. It is only true, according to, remember,
this is רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir. is the
one that is most restrictive, or I don’t know if restrictive is
the right word, but the one that most says the woman is
not her own legal entity, at least in terms of acquiring things,
she is seen as an extension of the husband. So he says
for her to be her own entity, even in this scenario, where
she is doing it for other people and the husband wants her
to be her own entity, it can only work if she actually
has a meaningful independent standing in this case. How does she have
a meaningful independent standing? She owns one of the houses here. And
if she owns one of the houses in her own right, right,
not she is living in her husband’s house, then for these הלכות
halachot we actually see her already as something of her own legal
entity. Okay, and therefore in that case she can represent herself. But
if she does not have any particular standing in this case to
be seen as, you know, as a sort of as her own
entity, so she is just, I mean, you know, in a normal
case, I don’t know, I’m just she is my daughter, I want
to give her something, but there is nothing that she is not
like not her own entity in that case, but there is nothing
that specifically makes her in that context seen as a person of
her own standing, then she is just seen as an extension of
the husband, okay, according to רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir Yes.
Does the house also belong to the husband?
Well, in this answer it doesn’t. In this answer, if the house
belongs to the husband, he cannot give it to his wife, but
if his wife has her own house, he can give it to
his wife.
So which type of property automatically becomes the husband’s as well?
Oh, you mean how come the house is not automatically the husband’s?
So that’s a good question. It could be, it could be that
she brought it into the marriage and it was explicitly stipulated that
the husband would have no rights over it, you know, and it
was specifically like a prenup, it was explicitly excluded from anything.
So in other words that would have to have been before the
marriage. After the marriage, anything that comes to
her—right, as far as רבי מאיר is concerned, after the marriage, right,
then it automatically gets transferred into—so now again, again the question is,
and I want to make this clear, even when we’re saying it
gets transferred, the question is an interesting one about how much does
it get transferred? Do we really mean the full title? Or do
we mean that the בעל אוכל פירות? ba’al ochel peirot? Right, this
discussion sounds like it means full title. Because here, who cares if
he’s entitled to benefit? The question is just taking possession of the
barrel of wine to be considered a partner and like who has
title. So the other point is that from this it also very
much seems—and look, that requires more elaboration which this גמרא is not
going into—but the simple sense of all this גמרא is not just
the aspect of אוכל פירות, ochel peirot, it sounds like it’s a
sense of full possession. Okay, now that’s point number one. Point number
two is that there’s a question how do we פוסק pasken at
the end of this. Right, it’s a debate of רב ושמואל. Rav
u’Shmuel. Normally we say הלכה כשמואל בדיני halacha k’Shmuel b’dinei that we
rule like שמואל Shmuel like in דיני ממונות dinei mamonot types of
cases. But so this is fundamentally a דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, although
it’s being applied to a case of איסור issur of נדרים. nedarim.
Okay, nevertheless the bulk of the ראשונים Rishonim are basically inclined to
פוסק pasken like שמואל Shmuel that we actually say, well actually, I’m
sorry, I might be misstating this. Let’s take a look at the
ר"ן. If you take a look at the ר"ן, go about eight
lines down in the wide lines, ולענין הלכה u’l’inyan halacha he says,
the widest lines, לגבי הלכה l’gabbei halacha פסק הנגיד רבינו שמואל הלוי
בשם רב עמרם גאון דהלכה כשמואל. pasak haNagid Rabbeinu Shmuel HaLevi b’shem
Rav Amram Gaon d’halacha k’Shmuel. Okay, I was right. And שמואל Shmuel
remember by the way is saying that the woman is less the
entity of the husband, right, that you can actually, you can interrupt
the flow, you can say על מנת שאין לבעלך רשות בהן. al
menat she’ein l’ba’alech reshut bahen. Okay, so we do rule like שמואל.
Shmuel. דאע"ג דפליגי הך לענין איסורא וקיימא לן כרב באיסורי אפילו הכי
כיון דעיקר פלוגתא בדינא תליא, d’af al gav d’pligi hach l’inyan issura
v’kayma lan k’Rav b’issurei afilu hachi keivan d’ikar plugta b’dina talya, since
it’s basically a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot question, אי אמרינן יד אשה
כיד בעלה לא נקטינן כשמואל דהלכתא כוותיה בדינא. ei amrinan yad ishah
k’yad ba’alah lo naktinan k’Shmuel d’hilchata k’vateih b’dina. We go like שמואל.
Shmuel. ועוד דרב כרבי מאיר ושמואל כרבנן הלכך נקטינן כוותיה. v’od d’Rav
k’Rebbe Meir u’Shmuel k’Rabbanan hilchach naktinan k’vateih.
Okay, and then in general, ועוד דסוגיין בעלמא כשמואל, v’od d’sugyan b’alma
k’Shmuel, in general the גמרא seems like שמואל, Shmuel, that it’s sufficient
to say על מנת שאין לבעלך רשות בהן, al menat she’ein l’ba’alech
reshut bahen, דעל מנת שאין לבעלך
רשות בהן לחוד מהני, d’al menat she’ein l’ba’alech reshut bahen l’chud mahani,
etc. etc. etc. Okay, and then he goes on and he says
there are others however that
פוסק—the—that pasken פוסק pasken like—like—like רב, Rav, and there’s a whole debate
exactly how we פוסק. pasken. All right, and other ways also about
reading exactly what that issue meant
about, about what do you call? מה דטירטי טאסי, mah detarti tasi,
he used another read for that as well, but you know what,
we won’t go into that. All right, so we’ll end with this
for today and pick up with the next משנה.